<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Business &#8211; लेट्स लर्न</title>
	<atom:link href="https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/tag/business/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn</link>
	<description>समाचार तपाइको हातमा</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 14:31:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/output-onlinepngtools-1.png</url>
	<title>Business &#8211; लेट्स लर्न</title>
	<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>WTO and Its impact on financial sector of Nepal</title>
		<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/01/12/everything-you-wanted-to-know-about-mega-citys/</link>
					<comments>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/01/12/everything-you-wanted-to-know-about-mega-citys/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[अमृत सुबेदी]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 16:39:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[खेलकुद]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[प्रबिधि]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cinema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sport]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[travel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[world]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://demo.themeansar.com/newsup/lite/?p=44</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“A financial service is any&#160;service of a financial nature offered buy a financial service supplier of a member. Financial services&#160;include all insurance and insurance related services, and all banking and other financial services”.&#160; Opening this section brings both&#160;positive and negative impacts on the sector itself&#160;and to the whole economy. Hence, opening the FSS, under WTO [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>“A financial service is any&nbsp;service of a financial nature offered buy a financial service supplier of a member. Financial services&nbsp;include all insurance and insurance related services, and all banking and other financial services”.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Opening this section brings both&nbsp;positive and negative impacts on the sector itself&nbsp;and to the whole economy. Hence, opening the FSS, under WTO provision, brings both opportunities and&nbsp;challenges. As some economists call FSS is the ‘brain of&nbsp;the economy’ and host of others accept it as&nbsp;‘engine of growth’. FSS is important for the economy as a whole since it allows financial transfer and&nbsp;payments. In other words a healthy and stable Financial Service Sector is essential for sustainable&nbsp;economic growth.</p>



<p>&nbsp;Unhealthy FSS can create the problem in this sector&nbsp;which will harm not only in this sector but as a whole economy and sometimes, even the region (as in&nbsp;East Asian Financial Crisis). (Malakar 2007). Under the&nbsp;Nepalese commitment on WTO, the Nepalese&nbsp;FSS is going to open fully by 2010 only. Under the commitment, the foreign banks are allowed to&nbsp;establish their branches in Nepal for whole sale banking.&nbsp;Opening the sector implies free entry or exit of&nbsp;foreign bank branches into Nepalese financial market. Entry of the foreign bank branches implies the&nbsp;entry of the new technology and latest experiences, by&nbsp;which the whole economic agents can enjoy better&nbsp;services in lower cost. But if once the crisis occur in&nbsp;FSS then the foreign owned banks do not help to&nbsp;reduce the impact of banking crisis but in some cases&nbsp;it makes the crisis worst (as in Argentina)(Blejer,&nbsp;2006).</p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading">IMPACT OF OPENING THE FSS</h1>



<p>Perhaps the pinnacle of opening or liberalization of service sector is the full CAC regime. For which it&nbsp;must fulfill some preconditions. CAC regime is essential to&nbsp;reap the benefit of liberalization because our&nbsp;concern of liberalizing the FSS is for the inflow of foreign capital. CAC regime is essential because capital&nbsp;will not come inside the country unless it has the assurance that it can go out (Sigdel, 2007). And only the&nbsp;full CAC regime assures it. At the present situation of&nbsp;dual exchange rate policy (i.e. fixed with India and&nbsp;flexible with others) we must be clear about it , that CAC, fixed exchange rate regime and independent&nbsp;monetary cum fiscal policy do not go together. The experience of other developing countries depicts that&nbsp;CAC would not be sustainable, if exchange rate is pegged (Sigdel, 2007).</p>



<p>Internationalization of FSS can bring both positive and&nbsp;negative impacts to this sector and to the whole economy.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">a) Positive Impacts</h2>



<p>Internationalization of FSS allows more stable sources of funds, it can help&nbsp;countries build&nbsp;more robust and efficient financial systems by introducing&nbsp;international&nbsp;practices&nbsp;and&nbsp;standards. It will help to improving the quality, efficiency&nbsp;and breadth of domestic financial&nbsp;institutions as well. Openness helps to increase&nbsp;competitiveness and in turn the economic&nbsp;growth. Some of the positive impacts&nbsp;of opening the&nbsp;FSS can be analyzed as follows:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">i) Access to international capital market:&nbsp;</h3>



<p>With the internationalization of the FSSs new foreign banks enter and establish their branches in the&nbsp;economy. They come with huge capital base, new technology, greater experiences, etc. which are&nbsp;important for a developing country like Nepal. As then insurgency has ended there will be a need for&nbsp;more investment for which we need huge capital, even if&nbsp;for the giant projects (like Arun III) we need&nbsp;some external resources which can be fulfilled in various&nbsp;ways but the established banks branches&nbsp;within the territory constitute the best source of such&nbsp;funds. Obviously the new technology implies&nbsp;better qualitative services at cheaper price. But we have to take care of the implications of&nbsp;technological innovations on the structure of financial services industries and market.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">ii) Enhance competition:</h3>



<p>Opening the sector is an open invitation to foreign players in Nepalese financial market. Higher the&nbsp;competition, larger the number of new players coming with&nbsp;international experiences, new&nbsp;technologies , bigger capital base, etc. for survive, the&nbsp;existing Financial Institutions (FIs) must&nbsp;increase their efficiency in term of size and quality. Hence, entry into WTO enhances the&nbsp;competitiveness.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">iii) Decrease the cost of capital and increases investment:</h3>



<p>Competition bounds the FIs to provide better service at&nbsp;cheaper price i.e. cost of capital (interest rate)&nbsp;has to be decreased. Opening the sector implies higher&nbsp;the competition with more advanced foreign&nbsp;competitors so the cost of capital decreases. As there&nbsp;is negative relationship between cost of capital&nbsp;and investment, a decrease interest rate would increase investment and the whole economy will be&nbsp;benefited.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">iv) Access to the international financial market:</h3>



<p>Opening the sector does not imply just entry of foreign FIs into the domestic market only, it also opens&nbsp;the door for the domestic FIs to enter into the rest of the world. Hence, after 2010 the domestic FIs will&nbsp;be able to establish their branches in other countries or they can expand their business throughout the&nbsp;world (at least in the WTO member countries).&nbsp;Though, initially it is hard to provide the financial services to the foreigners in foreign countries by the&nbsp;banks of developing countries like Nepal (due to the smaller capital base, lack of experiences, etc), but&nbsp;there is possibility to establish the branches in those parts of foreign countries where the Nepalese&nbsp;people (workers) more obviously prefers Nepalese banks. Even the FIs can provide the service for&nbsp;remittance. The remittance business is good at present in Nepal. The business it self is very big&nbsp;(remittance contributes around 16 percent of total GDP&nbsp;at present). At present, more that 69 percent of&nbsp;the total remittances is coming through informal channel (WB 2007). If the Nepalese FIs successed to&nbsp;channelize those remittances then the business of those FIs would grow significantly.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">v) Impact on debit and credit flow:</h3>



<p>In regard to Balance of Payment (BoP), WTO membership will result in greater flow of debit and credit.&nbsp;A report of NRB shows that from 2004/05 to 2015/16,&nbsp;flow of debit and credit are expected to increase&nbsp;by 155 and 150 percent respectively (on average). Since FIs are the mediator of such transaction, so&nbsp;the business of FIs flourishes by the sum of debit and&nbsp;credit (i.e. more than 300 percent) in 2015 /16&nbsp;comparative to 2004/05.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">vi) Nepal as a financial center:</h3>



<p>Nepal has a clear leverage in creation of international financial center that has ultimate goal to make&nbsp;Nepal “A Switzerland of Asia” (Collins, 1997). A poor and&nbsp;land locked country like Nepal with many&nbsp;constraints (like infrastructure and other supply side&nbsp;constrains) development as a financial center is&nbsp;comparatively easier and better way for economic development. If proper macro economic policy can&nbsp;be framed coupled with secure political and business environment there is possibility to become Nepal&nbsp;“A Switzerland of Asia”. This is only possible after accession to WTO. Hence, WTO membership fulfils&nbsp;the necessary condition for Nepal to be “A Switzerland of Asia” in terms of financial center.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">vii) Impact on the economy:</h3>



<p>With opening the FSS, experienced and more efficient banks come with better technology and huge&nbsp;capital base and the comparatively low efficient banks cannot survive in same ground, so the existing&nbsp;FIs, having less efficiency, will be compelled to diversing financial products and explore new products&nbsp;and new areas to survive. So, there are chances to establish the FIs in rural areas. Some banks have&nbsp;already started to think in this matter. Some banks have already started special schemes to lend to&nbsp;small and medium enterprises (SMEs). Presuming that foreign banks will be more interested in large&nbsp;size loans that go to big corporations. Forinstance, Himalayan Bank has revealed that it would start a&nbsp;special lending service for small borrowers in cooperation&nbsp;with the International Finance Corporation.&nbsp;This body operates under the World Bank and lends to the private sector. Machhapuchhre Bank has&nbsp;started its operation in rural areas. It has set up an&nbsp;Automatic Tellering Machine (ATM) in Jomsom.&nbsp;Nabil Bank has planned to set up branches in remote areas too. It has already set up an alliance with&nbsp;the postal saving bank to reach remote locations (Lamsal and Gautam, 2007). These scenarios show&nbsp;optimistic future for SMEs and agriculture sector, both&nbsp;of which are most important for the Nepalese&nbsp;economy. As mentioned before, openness increases competitiveness decreases, cost of capital,&nbsp;investment and economic activities increases and employment opportunities, finally the whole&nbsp;economy will be benefited.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">viii) CAC regime brings positive impacts:&nbsp;</h3>



<p>The effectiveness of capital account convertibility depends largely on the efficiency of the financial&nbsp;institutions at home. As per the WTO commitment, sooner or later full CAC regime is a must. For&nbsp;meaningful and favorable CAC regime, quality of the domestic financial institutions must be enhanced.&nbsp;Hence, CAC regime brings positive impacts on FSS under&nbsp;WTO provision but macroeconomic,&nbsp;financial and exchange rate polices must be put in right place. Liberalizing inflows should be sufficient&nbsp;to enable the country to draw on foreign savings to the optimum extent. Of course, capital will not&nbsp;come inside the country unless it as the assurance that&nbsp;it can go out (Sigdel, 2007).&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">b) Negative Impacts&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Experiences of other countries show that the financial distress is very harmful&nbsp;not&nbsp;for&nbsp;this&nbsp;sector only but the whole economy. In the present context of&nbsp;globalization, the economy is&nbsp;more open hence the financial crisis of an economy&nbsp;transfers more speedily and quickly to&nbsp;other economies, for example, the East&nbsp;Asian Financial&nbsp;Crisis in 1997. The crisis orginated in&nbsp;Bangkok (Thailand) which&nbsp;was started from the problem in banking, but most of the east&nbsp;Asian countries&nbsp;(except Singapore) were worst hit buy the crisis, hence the positive impact of&nbsp;liberalization of FSS brings many negative impacts as well. Some of the negative&nbsp;impacts&nbsp;are as follows:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">i) Higher risk of capital flight:</h3>



<p>As mentioned above, CAC regime is the pinnacle of the liberalization of FSS. CAC regime implies free&nbsp;entry and exit of the capital. Though the entry of capital has more positive impact, but the negative&nbsp;impact lie outflow of capital is very harmful to the developing countries like Nepal. Lack of capital is&nbsp;one of the common characteristics and problems of the developing country. In Todaro’s view, “A&nbsp;Country is poor, because it is poor”, due to lack of capital, investment is low and growth of the&nbsp;economy is low. Obviously the return of capital in the&nbsp;developed economy is more than LDCs. If there&nbsp;is CAC regime then the&nbsp;capital, whether it is big or small, capitalist invest it there- where the return is&nbsp;higher. CAC regime is more dangerous for Nepal because&nbsp;Nepal itself is situated between two giants&nbsp;and the fastest growing economies, China and India (having near to double digit growth rate).</p>



<p>Obviously, the return of the capital in those economies is more than the inflow in Nepal. If the&nbsp;capitalists are allowed then there are high chances to jump to those economies. Hence, the CAC&nbsp;regime creates a higher risk of capital flight.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">ii) Decrease in the profit and market share of domestic banks:</h3>



<p>As FSS opens, the new (foreign) players enter into the&nbsp;domestic financial market with better ideas,&nbsp;more knowledge and huge capital base so competitions increases. In the more competitive&nbsp;environment the existing FIs will be bound to provide services with interest spread rate (interest rate&nbsp;between lending and borrowing) which decreases the profit. As some FIs are working in break even&nbsp;situation, they will be collapsed.&nbsp;On the other hand, as in case of China, after 10 years from the WTO accession, it is estimated that the&nbsp;market share of foreign banks will be increased. Increase the share of foreign banks implies&nbsp;decreasing the share of domestic banks.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">iii) High potentialities of shifting the good credit worthy with high quality clients to the foreign&nbsp;banks :</h3>



<p>Due to better services, technologies, facilities and more&nbsp;innovative ideas the clients (especially the&nbsp;good creditworthy with high quality ) will shift to those&nbsp;incoming advanced foreign FIs. Leaving the less&nbsp;creditworthy clients and some business with the domestic&nbsp;banks. This probable shift is a major threat&nbsp;to domestic banks (Kim, 2002).&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">iv) Gap between the urban and rural areas widens further:</h3>



<p>Recent, data published by Nepal Rastra Bank (NRB) shows that the Cemercial Banks (CBs) are more&nbsp;urban centric. According to the data some economically&nbsp;active districts like Kathmandu, Parsa, Morang&nbsp;and Kaski have 71, 24, 24 and 47 CBs banks branches&nbsp;respectively. On the other hand in the whole&nbsp;far western development region there are just 20 branches of CBs. Opening the FSS would increase&nbsp;disparity as the incoming foreign bank branches will be least interested to go to the rural areas and the&nbsp;urban areas will be more resourceful and rural areas will&nbsp;become more drought. Hence, opening the&nbsp;FSSs will increases the disparity between rural and urban&nbsp;areas.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">v) High risk and cost and financial crisis:</h3>



<p>Without effective regulatory, supervisory regimes and appropriate macroeconomic policies,&nbsp;internationalization of financial sector is an open invitation for financial crisis. For example, the root&nbsp;cause of East Asian financial crisis was the serious mismanagement of the huge overseas borrowing&nbsp;by domestic (not foreign) banks and finance companies&nbsp;and business corporation (Kim, 2002). Liberal&nbsp;policy has been found the main cause for the huge financial crisis in the past. Cost of the crisis were&nbsp;too high, for example the cost of financial crisis of Argentina in 1980-82 was around 55 percent of&nbsp;GDP, similarly the cost was around 32-41 percent in Chile in 1981-83. Moreover the developed&nbsp;economies like Norway, Sweden, Finland and even the US&nbsp;were not free form the financial crisis and&nbsp;the cost were 3-4, 4-6, 8 and 2-5 percent of GDP in&nbsp;1987-89, 1992-93, 1991-93 and 1984-91&nbsp;respectively. The called “Black December” (financial crisis&nbsp;of Mexico in 1994) can be taken as a good&nbsp;example, of even the most resourceful (in term of human resource as well) economy not being able to&nbsp;block the crisis. The financial crisis of Mexico shocked&nbsp;the world and stunned the international financial&nbsp;community. A nation considered as a model of economic reform and good financial health was</p>



<p>suddenly bankrupt. Its international reserves had depleted, its currency was on free fall, it was about to&nbsp;default on its sovereign debt, and its banking system was on the verge of collapse. Uncertainty gripped&nbsp;the whole Latin American region (Garcia, 1997). From these experiences of the cost of such crises, we&nbsp;can learn the lesson for the likely worst scenario that Nepal may face from liberalization of FSS. To&nbsp;what extent, the LDCs like Nepal can tolerate such crisis is itself the subject of debate.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">vi) High chance to loose the monetary autonomy:&nbsp;</h3>



<p>Undoubtly the main motivating factor to enter the foreign FIs in an economy is ‘profit’. Such FIs are&nbsp;guided by there parent institution prefering the favorable situation for itself. The regulatory authority of&nbsp;the economy will be forced to accept their terms and conditions. And even the government is bound to&nbsp;make new policies as they suggest, no matter the policy&nbsp;is beneficial or harmful to the economy. In this&nbsp;way internationalization of the FSS may cause a loss monetary autonomy of domestic authorities.&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">vii) Internationalization creates the problem of overbanking and unfair trade practices:</h3>



<p>Overbanking suggests that there are already too many&nbsp;banks trying to attract business in a given&nbsp;financial market (Kono, Low, Luanga, Matto and Oshikawa, 1997). The overbanking creates many&nbsp;problems in the economy simultaneously. For example more the banks, more the cost and difficulties&nbsp;to regulate and supervision. On the other hand more players in the same market increase unhealthy&nbsp;competition. In the developing countries like Nepal, the&nbsp;licensing or liquidation regime cannot be&nbsp;accepted as an efficient tool.&nbsp;&nbsp;Hence due to internationalization of FSS, the economy has to face the&nbsp;crowding of FIs with unsound banking practices. Again&nbsp;protectionism can not be the best solution for it,&nbsp;for example in Russia out of 2150 banks, 450 were wound up in between 1995 and 1996. During the&nbsp;same period 200banks were liquidated in Argentina. In Korea and Malaysia merger have been&nbsp;encouraged. Experts believe, Nepal is facing the problem&nbsp;of overbanking in urban areas, even before&nbsp;internationalization. Hence, after opening the sector, it would increase further.&nbsp;</p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading">CONCLUSION&nbsp;</h1>



<p>Accession to WTO is not a matter of choice for the small, land-locked and donor dependent countries like&nbsp;Nepal. Internationalization of FSS brings both ‘benefit and cost’ where benefits are potential in the long&nbsp;run but the costs are immediate.&nbsp;The positive side of opening the FSS is that opening the door to international capital market would help&nbsp;overcome the ‘lack of capital’ and can help fulfill the dream of huge and ambitious projects (likes Arun III).&nbsp;But, it also opens the door to enter into the foreign financial markets for the Nepalese FIs. Due to the&nbsp;presence of more experienced and advanced players the&nbsp;competitiveness of the domestic FIs also&nbsp;enhances, by which the cost of capital decreases and&nbsp;investment friendly environment will be created.&nbsp;And finally the whole economy will be benefited. More over&nbsp;internationalization fulfils the necessary&nbsp;condition to become Nepal ‘A Switzerland of Asia’ in regard to the financial center.&nbsp;But the dark side of it cannot be ignored that internationalization has been the root cause for huge&nbsp;financial crisis in the past in other economies. From the existing domestic FI’s perspective, opening the&nbsp;FSS may be harmful; it may even cause collapse of the institutions. Sooner or later CAC regime has to be&nbsp;accepted, after internationalization of the Financial Service (FS) it causes the effects of capital flight which&nbsp;is obviously harmful to the capital lacking and developing&nbsp;countries like Nepal. Due to unbalanced growth&nbsp;it may create social evils as well. Finally, the overbanking&nbsp;creates unhealthy competition, which is harmful&nbsp;for the players of FSS and to the economy as well.</p>



<p>After accession to WTO, the only choice Nepal has is to mitigate the negative consequences and try to utilize potential benefits. By 2010, the Nepalese financial market is going to open fully for the wholesale banking to foreign FIs. In order to reap the benefit from it; an effective regulatory and supervisory regime must be established with appropriate macroeconomic policies. It would be prudent to review the tax policy, i.e. different tax rate for the FIs , which operates in urban and rural areas so as to motivate the FIs to go to the rural areas, which help to decrease the unbalance growth to some extent. To reap benefit from the full CAC regime, Nepal should open capital account along in consonance with the line of India. Moreover, for the provision of full CAC regime there are some preconditions as; (a) control fiscal deficit below 3 percent of GDP (b) maintain foreign exchange reserve at least 20 percent of GDP (c) control inflation rate within 2-3 percent (d) remove the fixed exchange rate regime</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/01/12/everything-you-wanted-to-know-about-mega-citys/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>नेपालमा वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारको प्रयास</title>
		<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/01/12/metro-citys-should-make-road-with-protection-in-mind/</link>
					<comments>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/01/12/metro-citys-should-make-road-with-protection-in-mind/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[अमृत सुबेदी]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 16:38:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[विचार]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://demo.themeansar.com/newsup/lite/?p=42</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[कुनैपनि मुलुकको अर्थव्यवस्थाको आधारस्तम्भ भनेको त्यस देशको वित्तीय क्षेत्र हो। कुशल वित्तीय मध्यस्थताको माध्यमद्वारा दिगो आर्थिक वृद्धि हासिल गर्ने कार्यमा अर्थव्यवस्थालाई प्रोत्साहित गर्ने काम वित्तीय क्षेत्रको हुने गर्दछ । आर्थिक स्रोतहरू लागत तथा जोखिमको न्यूनीकरण, अवसरको वृद्धि तथा विविधीकरण, स्रोतहरूको कुशल समायोजन तथा उत्पादनशीलता वृद्धि गर्दै आर्थिक वृद्धि गर्ने काममा आधुनिक वित्तीय प्रणालीले महत्वपूर्ण भूमिका [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>कुनैपनि मुलुकको अर्थव्यवस्थाको आधारस्तम्भ भनेको त्यस देशको वित्तीय क्षेत्र हो। कुशल वित्तीय मध्यस्थताको माध्यमद्वारा दिगो आर्थिक वृद्धि हासिल गर्ने कार्यमा अर्थव्यवस्थालाई प्रोत्साहित गर्ने काम वित्तीय क्षेत्रको हुने गर्दछ । आर्थिक स्रोतहरू लागत तथा जोखिमको न्यूनीकरण, अवसरको वृद्धि तथा विविधीकरण, स्रोतहरूको कुशल समायोजन तथा उत्पादनशीलता वृद्धि गर्दै आर्थिक वृद्धि गर्ने काममा आधुनिक वित्तीय प्रणालीले महत्वपूर्ण भूमिका खेल्छ । चुस्त तथा स्वस्थ्य वित्तीय प्रणालीले वास्तविक क्षेत्रको दिगोवृद्धि तथा अर्थव्यवस्थाका अनिश्चितता तथा अवरोध हटाउँदै राष्ट्रको मुख्य उद्देश्य आर्थिक विकास तथा गरिबी निवारण हासिल गर्न सक्ने बनाउँछ । आर्थिक विकासको पूर्वाधारका रूपमा वित्तीय क्षेत्र रहेको हुन्छ । वित्तीय क्षेत्र भनेको सरकारी निकायहरू, व्यावसायिक कार्यहरू तथा नागरिकहरूका लागि आवश्यक अल्पकालीन, मध्यकालीन तथा दीर्घकालीन अवधिका वित्तीय साधनहरूको माग र आपूर्तिको प्रबन्ध मिलाउने विस्तृत क्षेत्र हो । आर्थिक प्रगतिको सम्भावनालाई विनाअवरोध बिस्तार गर्न स्वस्थ र प्रभावकारी वित्तीय प्रणाली आवश्यक पर्दछ । यसरी उपलब्ध स्रोत र साधनकोप्रभावकारी परिचालन गर्न, लागत र जोखिमलाई उचित व्यवस्थापन गर्न, विविध सम्भावनाहरूलाई अवसरमा रूपान्तरण गर्न र समग्र उत्पादकत्वमा वृद्धि गरी आर्थिक संवृद्धि हासिल गर्न वित्तीय क्षेत्रले प्रमुख भूमिका खेलेको हुन्छ ।&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">नेपालमा वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारको विकासक्रम&nbsp;</h3>



<p>विश्व अर्थव्यवस्थामा सन् १९८० देखि आएकोउदारीकरणलाई नेपालको अर्थव्यवस्थाले आत्मसात गर्दाको समय सन् १९८० को मध्यदेखि नेपालमा वित्तीय सेवाहरूको कार्यक्षमता अभिवृद्धि गर्ने उद्देश्यले नेपालमा अनौपचारिक रूपमा वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रम सञ्चालनमा आयो । तत्पश्चात् बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय मध्यस्थकर्ताहरूलाई वित्तीय कारोबारको इजाजत प्रदान गर्ने सम्बन्धमा उदारीकरणको नीति अवलम्बन गरिएको थियो । त्यस अवस्थामा सरकारी स्वामित्वका दुई वाणिज्य बैङ्कहरू नेपाल बैङ्क लिमिटेड तथा राष्ट्रिय वाणिज्य बैङ्कको एकाधिकारी बजार संयन्त्रमा निजी क्षेत्रको बैङ्किङ संस्था सञ्चालनमा आउन सक्ने गरी वित्तीय क्षेत्रमा गरिएका प्रमुख सुधारहरू, जस्तो वाणिज्य बैङ्कहरूलाई व्याजदर निर्धारणमा पूर्ण स्वायत्तता प्रदान गरिनुतथा विकास बैङ्क, वित्त कम्पनी, सहकारी संस्था र गैरसरकारी संस्थाहरूलाई सर्तसहित निक्षेप स्वीकार गर्न स्वीकृति प्रदान गरिनु, चालुखाता पूर्ण रूपमा परिवत्र्यता एवं खुला बजार सञ्चालनमार्फत मौद्रिक नीतिको अप्रत्यक्ष उपकरणको प्रयोग वित्तीय क्षेत्रको बिस्तारका क्रममा अवलम्बन गरिएका केही महत्वपूर्ण व्यवस्थाहरू रहेका थिए । वि.सं. २०४२ सालमा नेपालको अर्थव्यवस्थामा देखा परेका भुक्तान सन्तुलनको प्रतिकूलतालाई अनुकूल बनाउन आन्तरिक प्रयत्नले मात्र सम्भव नहुने महसुस गरी तत्कालीन सरकारले अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय मुद्रा कोषसँग संरचनागत समायोजन सहुलियत लिएर संरचनात्मक समायोजन कार्यक्रम लागू ग¥यो । यसरी अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय मुद्रा कोषसँग सहयोग लिँदा कोषसँग गरिएका प्रतिबद्धताबाट नै नेपालमा आर्थिक उदारीकरण एवं वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारको कार्य प्रारम्भ भएको मान्न सकिन्छ । त्यस अवस्थामा वित्तीय क्षेत्रलाई सुसङ्गठित बनाइराख्न विगतमा अवलम्बन गरिएका नीतिगत व्यवस्थाहरू खास गरी निम्नलिखित उद्देश्यहरू निर्देशित थिए :</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />वित्तीय प्रणालीलाई बजारमुखी बनाउनु,&nbsp;</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />वित्तीय प्रणालीकोविकासमा निजी क्षेत्रलाई सहभागी बनाउनु,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />वित्तीय प्रणालीलाई प्रतिस्पर्धी बनाई दक्षता वृद्धि गर्नु,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />वित्तीय उपकरणहरूमा गुणात्मक सुधार ल्याई उपकरणहरूको उपलब्धता बढाउनु,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />मुलुकमा पुँजी बजारको विकास गर्नु आदि ।&nbsp;</p>



<p>यसरी बैङ्किङ क्षेत्रमा निजी क्षेत्रको प्रवेशलाई आमन्त्रण एवं बैदेसिक लगानी बैङ्किङ क्षेत्रमा प्रवेशसँगै वित्तीय क्षेत्रलाई बढी प्रतिस्पर्धी, सक्षम र स्वस्थ्य बनाई सर्वसाधारणलाई छिटोछरितो, सर्वसुलभ र स्तरीय बैङ्किङ सेवा प्रदान गर्न केन्द्रीय बैङ्ककोभूमिका तथा जिम्मेदारी बिस्तार हुन पुग्यो। सरकारी स्वामित्वका बैङ्कहरूको समग्र वित्तीय स्थिति दिनप्रतिदिन प्रतिकूल हुँदैजान थाल्यो । IMF को SAF न्तर्गत वित्तीय क्षेत्रलाई उदार बनाउने नीतिगत व्यवस्थाअनुरूप केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको प्रत्यक्ष नियमन र सुपरीवेक्षणकोभूमिका खुकुलो पार्दै लगियो । खास गरी वाणिज्य बैङ्कहरूले सन् १९८० देखि १९९० को अवधिमा विदेशी मुद्रामा निक्षेप स्वीकार गर्ने व्यवस्था, मौद्रिक नियन्त्रणका लागि साप्ताहिक रूपमा ट्रेजरी बिलको बोलकबोल, खुला बजारको सञ्चालन, कर्जा सूचना केन्द्रको स्थापना, नेपाल औद्योगिक विकास निगमलाई केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको नियमनको परिधिभित्र ल्याउने नीतिगत सुधार भएको देखिन्छ । अनौपचारिक वित्तीय क्षेत्रको सुधारलाई निरन्तरताको क्रममा वित्त कम्पनी ऐन, २०४८, सहकारी ऐन, २०४८, विकास बैङ्क ऐन, २०५३, कम्पनी ऐन, २०४८ आए । बजारमा नयाँ–नयाँ वित्तीय उपकरणमार्फत ग्राहकहरूलाई वित्तीय सेवा र सुविधा पनि उपलब्ध हुन थाल्यो। यस अवधिमा नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कले केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको हैसियतले वित्तीय क्षेत्रको सङ्ख्यात्मक उपस्थितिलाई व्यवस्थित गर्न तथा वित्तीय प्रणालीलाई सुदृढीकरण गर्न विभिन्न प्रकारका प्रयासहरू गरेको देखिन्छ । बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय संस्थाहरूलाई प्रभावकारी रूपमा नियमन तथा सुपरीवेक्षण गर्न अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय सुपरीवेक्षण संस्था वासेलद्वारा प्रतिपादित सुपरीवेक्षणको मुख्य सिद्धान्त&nbsp; लाई आधार बनाई पुँजीकोष, वैधानिक तरलता, कर्जा वर्गीकरण तथा जोखिम कोषको व्यवस्था लगायतका Prudential Norms जारी भए । साथैयस अवधिमा UNDP को सहयोगमा NRB र RBB मा देखिएका समस्याहरूको अध्ययन तथा विश्लेषण गर्न Commercial Bank Problem Analysis and Strategy Study को काम भयो र सोही अध्ययन प्रतिवेदनका आधारमा पुँजी थप लगायतका कामहरू गरिए ।&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">आपचारिक वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रम&nbsp;</h4>



<p>वित्तीय क्षेत्रको सुधारमा खास गरी वाणिज्य बैङ्कहरूको सुधारको प्रसङ्गलेनै प्रमुख स्थान पाएको हुन्छ । सन् १९८० देखि नै आर्थिक उदारीकरणको नीतिलाई प्रवद्र्धन गर्न सरकारका तर्फबाट चालिएका आर्थिक सुधारका प्रयासहरूले मात्र वित्तीय सुधारको आवश्यकता परिपूर्ति हुने अवस्था देखिएन । नियमित रूपमा वित्तीय क्षेत्रलाई व्यवस्थित पार्न र केन्द्रीय बैङ्कबाट भएका प्रयासबाट मात्र लक्ष्य हासिल गर्न कठिन हुने देखियो । यसका साथै वित्तीय क्षेत्रको ठूलो हिस्सा ओगटेको नेपाल बैङ्क लिमिटेड&nbsp; र राष्ट्रिय वाणिज्य बैङ्क झन् सङ्कटतिर धकेलिनु, देशमा नयाँ बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय संस्थाहरू थपिनु र स्थापनाको केही वर्षमा नै निजी क्षेत्रका बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय संस्थाहरूमा समेत विविध समस्याहरू देखा पर्नु आदि कारणले वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारका लागि सरकार तथा केन्द्रीय बैङ्कले छुट्टैर महत्वपूर्ण प्याकेज ल्याउनुपर्ने आवश्यकता भयो । वाणिज्य बैङ्कमा सञ्चालित हिसाब मिलान परियोजना र अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय लेखापरीक्षण संस्थाले सन् २००० मा नेपाल बैङ्क लिमिटेडको लेखापरीक्षण गरी विभिन्न समस्या, जस्तो– संस्थागत सुशासन कमजोर रहेको, लगानी प्रक्रियामा त्रुटि, भ्रष्ट आचरणका कर्मचारी, व्यवस्थापकीय व्यावसायिक तथा रणनीतिक योजनाको अभाव जस्ता समस्या देखाई बैङ्क प्राविधिक रूपमा टाट पल्टिने स्थितिमा पुगेको प्रतिवेदन सार्वजनिक ग¥यो । यसरी तत्कालीन अवस्थामा ७०% बजार हिस्सा ओगटेका वाणिज्य बैङ्कहरूको दयनीय अवस्थालाई सुधार गरी विश्वसनीय वित्तीय मध्यस्थतालाई सुदृढीकरण गर्ने मुख्य उद्देश्यसहित सरकारले स्पष्ट मार्गचित्र सहितको वित्तीय सुधार रणनीति, २०५७ जारी ग¥यो । यसरी वित्तीय क्षेत्रको सुधारमा विभिन्न सरकारी तथा बैदेसिक सहयोग परिचालन भएको छ । नेपालमा सञ्चालित वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रमलाई मुख्य रूपमा सहयोग पु¥याउने राष्ट्रिय तथा अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय निकायमा नेपाल सरकार, नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्क, एसियाली विकास बैङ्क, अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय मुद्रा कोष, विश्व बैङ्क र अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय विकास विभाग प्रमुख रहेका छन् । सरकारद्वारा २०५७ मा जारी वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार रणनीतिले जोड दिएका मुख्य उद्देश्यहरू निम्नलिखित छन्ः&nbsp;</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको सुदृढीकरण गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्किङ क्षेत्रमा विद्यमान लेखा तथा लेखापरीक्षण व्यवस्थामा सुधार गर्ने,&nbsp;</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />पर्याप्त पारदर्शिता र प्रतिस्पर्धाका माध्यमबाट वित्तीय अनुशासन कायम गर्ने,&nbsp;</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />वित्तीय सम्झौताहरू लागूगर्ने सम्बन्धमा कानुनी र अदालती प्रक्रिया सुधार गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />गरिबी निवारणमा प्रोत्साहन गर्ने कार्यक्रम सञ्चालनमा वित्तीय हस्तक्षेपलाई केन्द्रित गर्ने आदि ।</p>



<p>नेपाल सरकारको रणनीतिपत्रले नेपालको केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको महत्वपूर्ण जिम्मेवारी, जवाफदेहिता तथा भूमिका वृद्धि गरेको छ । नेपाल सरकारले नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कले खेल्न सक्ने भूमिका, जस्तो बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय संस्थाको नियमन तथा निरीक्षण र सुपरीवेक्षण गर्ने कार्यमा पूर्ण रूपले सहयोग पु¥याएको छ । घोषित उद्देश्य हासिल गर्नका लागि नेपाल सरकारको रणनीति पेपरमा उल्लिखित रणनीतिहरू निम्नलिखित छन्ः</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्किङ एवं वित्तीय प्रतिस्पर्धामा अभिवृद्धि गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />वित्तीय एवं बैङ्किङ कानुनकोसंरचनामा सुधार गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />नेपाल राष्ट्रबैङ्ककोनिरीक्षण तथा सुपरीवेक्षण क्षमतामा अभिवृद्धि गर्ने</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />पर्याप्त प्रतिस्पर्धा एवं पारदर्शिताकोअनुशरण गरी वित्तीय अनुशासन प्रवद्र्धन गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />नेपाल बैङ्क लिमिटेड र राष्ट्रिय वाणिज्य बैङ्ककोव्यवस्थापन सुधार गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />नेपाल औद्योगिक विकास निगम र कृषि विकास बैङ्क लि. कोव्यवस्थापन सुधार गर्ने</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />क्षेत्रीय रूपमा वित्तीय आवश्यकताकोपरिपूर्ति गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />क्षेत्रीय विकास बैङ्कहरूकोस्थापना गर्ने</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />ग्रामीण विकास बैङ्ककोपुनर्संरचना गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />साख मूल्याङ्कन संस्थाकोस्थापना गर्ने,&nbsp;</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />कर्जा सूचना केन्द्रकोस्थापना गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />AMC को स्थापना (समस्या व्यवस्थापन कम्पनी) गर्ने</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्कर्स प्रशिक्षण केन्द्रको पुनर्संरचना गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />ऋण असुली न्यायाधीकरणको स्थापना गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />लेखा एवं लेखापरीक्षण प्रणालीमा सुधार गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />पुँजी स्वामित्व ढाँचाकोपुनरावलोकन गर्ने आदि ।&nbsp;</p>



<p>घोषित उद्देश्य प्राप्तिका लागि नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कलेवित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रमलाई दुई चरणमा बाँडेकोथियो ।&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">(क) पहिलोचरण&nbsp;</h4>



<p>प्हिलो चरण अन्तर्गत वित्तीय क्षेत्र प्राविधिक सहयोग कार्यक्रम थियो। यो कार्यक्रम विश्व बैङ्कको अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय विकास संस्था को सहयोगमा सन् २००३ को अप्रिलदेखि सुरु भई सन् २००७ जुनसम्म सञ्चालन भयो । यसको कुल लागत ३.१ करोड अमेरिकी डलर थियो । त्यस मध्ये १.६० करोड&nbsp; DFID को ऋण र १ करोड डलर अनुदान थियो। त्यसमा सरकारी अनुदान ४१ लाख डलर थियो । पहिलो चरणको कार्यक्रमले जोड दिएका सुधारका क्षेत्र निम्नलिखित थिए :</p>



<p>१. नेपाल राष्ट्रबैङ्कको रिइन्जिनियरिङ</p>



<p>२. दुई ठूला वाणिज्य बैङ्क NRB र RBB को पुनर्संरचना र&nbsp;</p>



<p>३. समग्र वित्तीय क्षेत्रकोक्षमता अभिवृद्धि ।&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>(ख) दोस्रोचरण&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>पहिलो चरणको कार्यक्रमलाई नै निरन्तरता प्रदान गर्न दोस्रो चरणको कार्यक्रम लागू गरियो । यसका लागि IDA सँग ऋण सम्झौता सन् २००७ को जुनमा भयो । सो परियोजनाको अवधि सन् २००९ को अप्रिलसम्म थियो। त्यसअन्तर्गत IDA सँग ६.८५ करोड अमेरिकी डलर ऋण तथा नेपाल सरकारको ७० लाख डलर अनुदानमा परियोजना सञ्चालन गर्ने लक्ष्य लिइएको थियो । त्यस परियोजना अन्तर्गत जनशक्ति विकास, लेखाप्रणालीमा सुधार, नियमन तथा सुपरीवेक्षणका क्षेत्रमा थप सुदृढीकरण, सूचना तथा प्रविधिको गुणस्तरमा विकास लगायतका कार्यक्रममा उपरोक्त रकम खर्च गर्ने कार्यक्रम बनाइएको थियो। हालका दिनमा वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारमा विदेशी सहयोगमा सञ्चालित कार्यक्रम रोकिए तापनि नेपाल सरकार तथा नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कले सुधार कार्यक्रमलाई निरन्तरता दिइरहेका छन्। अझैपनि वित्तीय क्षेत्र पूर्णरूपमा सक्षम तथा सबल रूपमा सञ्चालन हुन नसकिरहेको अवस्थामा यसको सुधारको निरन्तरताको सान्दर्भिकता रहिरहेको छ । सरकारी स्वामित्वमा रहेका दुई ठूला बैङ्कहरू NRB र RBB अझैपनि स्वतन्त्र समूहको व्यावस्थापनमा छाडन सक्ने अवस्था छैन । अझैपनि यी बैङ्कहरूको पुँजीकोष ऋणात्मक छ । नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कको नियमन तथा सुपरीवेक्षण कार्यमा बढ्दो वित्तीय संस्थाहरूको सङ्ख्या तथा नयाँ वित्तीय उपकरणको प्रयोगले चुनौती थप्दै लगेकोछ । वित्तीय क्षेत्रको क्षमता अभिवृद्धि कार्यको निरन्तरताको आवश्यकता अझैपनि उत्तिकैछ । जस्तो ग्रामीण क्षेत्रमा वित्तीय पहुँच, ठूला मेघा परियोजना स्रोतको सुनिश्चिता आदि विषयमा सुधारको औचित्य कम भएको छैन । यिनै तथ्यलाई मध्यनजर गर्दै नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कले मौद्रिक नीति, २०६७÷६८ जारी गर्नेक्रममा वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रमलाई निरन्तरता दिएकोछ । हालसम्म वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रमबाट प्राप्त उपलब्धि विदेशी दातृ संस्थाहरू, नेपाल सरकार र केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको समन्वयमा भएका प्रयास एवं ठूलो लागतमा सञ्चालित वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधार कार्यक्रमका सम्बन्धमा विभिन्न पक्षबाट फरक–फरक प्रतिक्रिया आएको पाइन्छ । ठूलो लागतसहित सञ्चालित सुधार कार्यक्रमले लक्षित उद्देश्य समयमा नै प्राप्त गर्न नसक्नु, राजनीतिक क्षेत्रको हस्तक्षेपले सुधारको कार्यक्रममा व्यावसायिकता नहुनु, लागतको तुलनामा उपलब्धि कम हुनुआदि अवस्थालाई मात्र ध्यान केन्द्रित गर्ने समूहले सुधार कार्यक्रमप्रति असन्तुष्टि जाहेर गरेका छन् । अर्कोतर्फ झन्डै धरासायी अवस्थामा पुगेका सरकारी बैङ्कहरू एवं कठिन वातावरणीय परिवेशमा सञ्चालित समग्र वित्तीय प्रणालीलाई सुरक्षित रूपमा अहिलेको अवस्थामा ल्याइपु¥याएकोमा सन्तोष व्यक्त गर्ने पक्षहरू पनि प्रशस्त देखिन्छन्। यसरी जेजस्ता कमीकमजोरी देखिए पनि वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारको उपलब्धिलाई निम्नलिखित तथ्यगत आधारमा प्रस्तुत गर्न सकिन्छ ः&nbsp;</p>



<p>(क) नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कको पुनर्संरचनातर्फ तत्कालीन नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्क ऐन, २०१२ मा उल्लिखित उद्देश्य, संरचना एवं कानुनी व्यवस्थाबाट वित्तीय क्षेत्र सुधारका लक्ष्यहरू प्राप्त गर्न प्रायः असम्भव भएकोले नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्क ऐनको प्रस्तावनामा नै परिवर्तन गरी केन्द्रीय बैङ्कलाई सहायक कार्यबाट&nbsp; प्रमुख कार्य मा केन्द्रित गर्ने कार्य भयो। नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कलाई पारदर्शीर शीघ्र निर्णय गर्न सक्ने सङ्गठनका रूपमा स्थापित गर्न बैङ्कको स्वायत्तताका लागि विशेष व्यवस्थाहरू गरिए । NRB को पुनर्संरचना कार्यक्रमले जोड दिएका मुख्य विषयहरू निम्नलिखित छन्ः</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />मानव साधनकोविकास गर्ने,&nbsp;</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />नेपाल राष्ट्रबैङ्ककोनियमन व्यवस्था र निरीक्षण तथा सुपरीवेक्षण प्रणालीलाई अझ बढी सशक्त एवं प्रभावकारी&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;बनाउने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्ककोकार्यका आधारमा साङ्गठनिक पुनर्संरचना गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्कलाई कम्प्युटराइज गर्ने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्ककोलेखाप्रणालीलाई अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय मापदण्डअनुरूपकोबनाउने,</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f449.png" alt="👉" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />बैङ्ककोकार्यलाई सरल, सहज बनाउँदैकेन्द्रीय बैङ्कलाई चुस्त बनाउने आदि ।&nbsp;</p>



<p>नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कको सङ्गठनात्मक संरचनामा परिवर्तन गरी मुख्य चार किसिमको कार्यगत आधारमा वर्गीकरण गर्ने काम भएको छ ः मौद्रिक तथा विनिमय नीतिको सञ्चालन, बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय संस्थाको नियमन तथा सुपरीवेक्षण, सहायक सेवा एवं मानव संसाधनको क्षमता अभिवृद्धि रहेका छन् । बैङ्कको कामकारबाहीलाई चुस्त र छरितो बनाउन, कर्मचारीको उत्पादकत्व बढाउन तथा कर्मचारीबाटै गुणस्तरीय सेवा प्रदान गर्न विभिन्न चरणमा स्वेच्छिक अवकास योजना कार्यान्वयन एवं नियमित अनिवार्य अवकास योजना लागू गरियो । नयाँ कर्मचारी विनियमावली, २०६२ लागू गरिसकेको र त्यसको समयानुकूल संशोधन समेत गरिँदैछ । विदेशी मानव संसाधन सल्लाहकारको सहयोगमा मानव संसाधन विकासका लागि योजना, तालिम, जनशक्ति स्तर पहिचान र विकास जस्ता कार्यहरू भइरहेका छन्। NRB को सुपरीवेक्षण कार्यलाई प्रभावकारी बनाउन सुपरीवेक्षण विनियमावली, २०५९ Offsite/Onsite Mannual तयार गरी कार्यान्वयन गरिएको छ । नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कको लेखापरीक्षण कार्य अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय मापदण्डअनुसार समयमा नै सम्पन्न गरिएको छ । IT/MIS प्रशासन सार्वजनिक प्रशासनसम्बन्धी पत्रिकालाई व्यवस्थित र प्रभावकारी बनाउन विदेशी Consultant को सहयोगमा विभिन्न सुधार कार्यक्रम सञ्चालन गरिएका छन् । दोस्रो चरणको कार्यक्रम अन्तर्गत लेखाप्रणाली व्यवस्थित गर्न ७ जना चार्टड एकाउन्टेन्टको कार्यदल गठन गरी आवश्यक पूर्वाधारहरू तयार गर्ने काम भएको छ । नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्क ऐन, २०५८ कोदफा ८६(क) देखि ८६(ठ) सम्मका प्रावधानहरू थप गरी बैङ्क तथा वित्तीय संस्थाहरूलाई समस्याग्रस्त घोषणा गर्न सक्ने अधिकार केन्द्रीय बैङ्कलाई प्रदान गरिएको छ । नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कको स्वामित्वमा रहेका राष्ट्रिय बिमा संस्थान, पूर्वाञ्चल ग्रा.वि.बैङ्क, नागरिक लगानी कोष आदिको सेयर विक्री गरिएको छ । दामासाही सम्बन्धी ऐन, २०६३ तथा सम्पत्ति शुद्धीकरण ऐन, २०६४ जारी भई लागू भएका छन्। केन्द्रीय बैङ्कको कर्तव्य तथा उतरदायित्वलाई जिम्मेवारीपूर्वक निर्वाह गर्न नेपाल राष्ट्र बैङ्कको रणनीति योजना २००६–१० तर्जुमा भई कार्यान्वयनमा आएको छ । यसमा NRB को भिजन, मिसन, उद्देश्यहरू, रणनीतिहरू, कार्यहरू तथा कार्यसम्पादन मूल्याङ्कनहरू राखिएका छन्।</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/01/12/metro-citys-should-make-road-with-protection-in-mind/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
