<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>होमपेज &#8211; लेट्स लर्न</title>
	<atom:link href="https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/category/%E0%A4%B9%E0%A5%8B%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%9C/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn</link>
	<description>समाचार तपाइको हातमा</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 14:23:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/output-onlinepngtools-1.png</url>
	<title>होमपेज &#8211; लेट्स लर्न</title>
	<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Essence and Determinants of Ethics</title>
		<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2023/09/09/hello-world/</link>
					<comments>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2023/09/09/hello-world/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[अमृत सुबेदी]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 11:00:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[होमपेज]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/?p=1</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ethics is the branch of philosophy that deals with moral principles and values that govern human behavior. It is concerned with what is right or wrong, good or bad, and just or unjust. Ethics is a branch of philosophy that explores questions about right and wrong, good and bad, and what actions and behaviors are [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Ethics is the branch of philosophy that deals with moral principles and values that govern human behavior. It is concerned with what is right or wrong, good or bad, and just or unjust. Ethics is a branch of philosophy that explores questions about right and wrong, good and bad, and what actions and behaviors are just or unjust. It is concerned with the moral principles and values that guide human behavior and seeks to provide a framework for making ethical decisions.</p>



<p>At its core, ethics is about understanding what it means to be a good person and to live a good life. It is concerned with the development of character, virtues, and moral reasoning skills that enable individuals to make ethical decisions and behave in an ethical manner.</p>



<p>Ethical principles and values can be influenced by a variety of factors, including cultural and social norms, personal beliefs and values, and religious and spiritual traditions. These principles and values are often deeply ingrained and can be difficult to change. However, ethical principles and values can also be developed and refined through education, self-reflection, and engagement with ethical issues and debates.</p>



<p>There are many different ethical theories and frameworks that can be used to guide ethical decision-making. Some of these include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Deontological ethics, which focuses on the moral rules and duties that individuals have, regardless of their consequences.</li>



<li>Utilitarian ethics, which focuses on the greatest good for the greatest number of people.</li>



<li>Virtue ethics, which focuses on developing virtuous character traits such as honesty, compassion, and courage.</li>



<li>Care ethics, which emphasizes the importance of caring for others and relationships in ethical decision-making.</li>
</ul>



<p>In addition to these theories, there are also a variety of ethical issues and debates that are currently being discussed and debated, such as the ethics of artificial intelligence, climate change, and genetic engineering.</p>



<p>Ultimately, ethics is about living a life of integrity and making decisions that are consistent with one&#8217;s values and principles. It is about striving to be a good person and to do the right thing, even when it may be difficult or unpopular. By embracing ethics and ethical decision-making, individuals can help create a more just and compassionate world.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Essence of ethics</h3>



<p>The essence of ethics is the study of moral principles and values that guide human behavior. Ethics seeks to answer questions about what is morally right or wrong, good or bad, and just or unjust. It helps us to determine what actions are right or wrong, and what values should guide our behavior.</p>



<p>It is concerned with questions such as what is right or wrong, good or bad, and just or unjust. At its core, ethics is about understanding what it means to be a good person and to live a good life.</p>



<p>Ethics seeks to provide a framework for making ethical decisions, based on an understanding of fundamental principles and values. These principles and values can be influenced by a variety of factors, including cultural and social norms, personal beliefs and values, and religious and spiritual traditions. They help individuals to make decisions that are consistent with their personal sense of morality.</p>



<p>Ethics is important because it helps individuals and societies to establish standards of behavior that are fair, just, and respectful of human dignity. It provides a basis for evaluating the actions of individuals and institutions, and helps to promote social harmony and cooperation. Ethical behavior also helps to build trust and respect, both of which are essential for healthy relationships and social interactions.</p>



<p>The study of ethics is a complex and multifaceted endeavor, with many different theories and frameworks for understanding ethical issues and dilemmas. Some of the key ethical theories include deontological ethics, utilitarian ethics, virtue ethics, and care ethics, among others. These theories provide a basis for evaluating different ethical dilemmas and making decisions that are consistent with one&#8217;s own values and principles.</p>



<p>In summary, the essence of ethics is the study of moral principles and values that guide human behavior. It is concerned with questions about what is right or wrong, good or bad, and just or unjust. Ethics provides a framework for making ethical decisions and establishing standards of behavior that are fair, just, and respectful of human dignity. It is an essential component of healthy relationships and social interactions, and helps to promote social harmony and cooperation.</p>



<p><strong>Here are the some key points to summarize the essence of ethics.</strong></p>



<ol>
<li>Ethics is the study of moral principles and values that guide human behavior.</li>



<li>It is concerned with questions about what is right or wrong, good or bad, and just or unjust.</li>



<li>Ethics provides a framework for making ethical decisions based on an understanding of fundamental principles and values.</li>



<li>These principles and values can be influenced by a variety of factors, including cultural and social norms, personal beliefs and values, and religious and spiritual traditions.</li>



<li>Ethics helps individuals and societies to establish standards of behavior that are fair, just, and respectful of human dignity.</li>



<li>It provides a basis for evaluating the actions of individuals and institutions and helps to promote social harmony and cooperation.</li>



<li>Ethical behavior helps to build trust and respect, both of which are essential for healthy relationships and social interactions.</li>



<li>There are many different ethical theories and frameworks for understanding ethical issues and dilemmas, including deontological ethics, utilitarian ethics, virtue ethics, and care ethics, among others.</li>



<li>These theories provide a basis for evaluating different ethical dilemmas and making decisions that are consistent with one&#8217;s own values and principles.</li>



<li>Ultimately, the essence of ethics is about living a life of integrity and making decisions that are consistent with one&#8217;s values and principles.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Determinants of ethics</strong></h3>



<p>The determinants of ethics are the factors that influence moral behavior. These can include cultural, social, religious, and personal factors. The cultural and social values of a particular community or society may shape its ethical principles. Religion may also play a role in shaping ethical principles. Personal factors such as upbringing, experiences, and education can also influence ethical behavior.</p>



<p>The determinants of ethics are the factors that influence an individual&#8217;s moral principles and values. These factors can vary depending on the individual, their culture, and their environment. Here are some of the key determinants of ethics:</p>



<ol>
<li>Cultural and social norms: Cultural and social norms can play a significant role in shaping an individual&#8217;s ethical beliefs and values. Different cultures and societies have different norms and values that are considered ethical or moral.</li>



<li>Personal beliefs and values: Personal beliefs and values can also influence an individual&#8217;s ethical principles. These may be shaped by personal experiences, upbringing, education, and other factors.</li>



<li>Religious and spiritual traditions: Religious and spiritual traditions can provide a framework for ethical principles and values. They may offer specific guidance on what is right or wrong based on religious teachings and doctrines.</li>



<li>Professional codes of ethics: Many professions have established codes of ethics that guide the behavior of individuals in that profession. These codes may include standards for professional conduct, confidentiality, and conflict of interest.</li>



<li>Laws and regulations: Laws and regulations may also influence ethical behavior. They establish legal boundaries and consequences for certain behaviors, which can influence an individual&#8217;s ethical decision-making.</li>



<li>Personal conscience: An individual&#8217;s personal conscience, or inner sense of right and wrong, can also influence ethical decision-making. This may be based on an individual&#8217;s personal values and principles.</li>



<li>Peer pressure and social influence: Peer pressure and social influence can also impact ethical decision-making. Individuals may conform to the expectations of their peers or society, even if it conflicts with their personal ethical principles.</li>



<li>Economic and financial considerations: Economic and financial considerations can also influence ethical decision-making. Individuals may prioritize financial gain over ethical principles, or they may feel pressure to act unethically in order to meet financial targets.</li>



<li>Environmental factors: Environmental factors, such as the physical environment or the availability of resources, can also impact ethical decision-making. For example, individuals living in poverty may be more likely to engage in unethical behavior in order to meet their basic needs.<br>In summary, the determinants of ethics are the factors that influence an individual&#8217;s moral principles and values. These factors may include cultural and social norms, personal beliefs and values, religious and spiritual traditions, professional codes of ethics, laws and regulations, personal conscience, peer pressure and social influence, economic and financial considerations, and environmental factors. Understanding these determinants can help individuals to make ethical decisions that are consistent with their values and principles.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2023/09/09/hello-world/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>बासेल १ (Basel 1)</title>
		<link>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/03/01/the-heart-of-nintendos-new-console-isnt-the-switch/</link>
					<comments>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/03/01/the-heart-of-nintendos-new-console-isnt-the-switch/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[अमृत सुबेदी]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 11:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[होमपेज]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://demo.themeansar.com/newsup/lite/?p=94</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[जमर्नीमा ‘व्यान्खाउस हरस्ट्याट’ बैंकले अत्यन्तै उच्च जोखिम उठाएर बिदेशी बिनिमय सम्बन्धि कारोवार गरिरहेको थियो । कारोवारको सिलसिलामा आफ्नो पुँजीको तीन गुणाभन्दा बढिको जोखिम उठाइ सकेको थियो ।बैंक नियमन निकायले यो कुरा थाहा पायो । र, यस्ता क्रियाकलापले बैकिङ क्षेत्रमा ठूलो जोखिम निम्तिने ठानेर २६ जुन १९७४ का दिन त्यो बैंक बन्द गर्ने निर्णय गर्यो । [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>जमर्नीमा ‘व्यान्खाउस हरस्ट्याट’ बैंकले अत्यन्तै उच्च जोखिम उठाएर बिदेशी बिनिमय सम्बन्धि कारोवार गरिरहेको थियो । कारोवारको सिलसिलामा आफ्नो पुँजीको तीन गुणाभन्दा बढिको जोखिम उठाइ सकेको थियो ।<br>बैंक नियमन निकायले यो कुरा थाहा पायो । र, यस्ता क्रियाकलापले बैकिङ क्षेत्रमा ठूलो जोखिम निम्तिने ठानेर २६ जुन १९७४ का दिन त्यो बैंक बन्द गर्ने निर्णय गर्यो ।<br><br>बैंक बन्द भएपछि त्यससँग बिदेशी बिनिमय कारोवार गरेका अन्य बैंकले भुक्तानी पाएनन् । जुन जोखिमलाई आज पनि बैंकिङ क्षेत्रमा हरस्ट्याट (सेट्टलमेण्ट रिस्क) जोखिम भन्ने गरिन्छ । ‘ब्रेटन उड्स सिस्टम्’ हटेकाले यो बैंक असफल हुन पुगेको ठानिन्छ ।<br><br><strong>के हो ब्रेटन उड्स सिस्टम् ?</strong><br>सन् १९४४ को जुलाईमा ४४ देशका प्रतिनिधि ब्रेटन उड्समा मौद्रिक तथा बित्तीय सम्मेलनमा भाग लिन जम्मा भए, जसलाई ब्रेटन उड्स सम्मेलन नाम दिइएको थियो ।<br><br>उक्त सम्मेलनले ‘इन्टरनेश्नल मनेटरी फण्ड’ (आईएमएफ) र&nbsp; ‘इन्टरनेश्नल बैंक फर रिकन्सट्रक्सन एण्ड डेभ्लपमेण्ट’ को स्थापना गर्ने निर्णय गर्यो ।<br><br>त्यस्तैगरी, ती देशमा सुन र अमेरिकी (युएस) डलरमा आधारित स्थीर मुद्रा बिनिमय प्रणाली लागू गर्ने निर्णय पनि गर्यो । १ औन्स सुन बराबर ३५ यूएस डलर कायम गरिएको थियो । १ ट्रोय औन्समा ३१.१०३५ ग्राम हुन्छ ।</p>



<p>आईएमएफलाई भुक्तानी असुन्तलन आएमा हस्तक्षेप गर्नका लागि अधिकार दिइएको थियो । यहि स्थीर मुद्रा बिनिमय प्रणालीलाई ‘ब्रेटन उड्स सिस्टम’ भनिन्छ ।</p>



<p>यसपछि युएस डलरलाई सबैले संचित मुद्राका रुपमा लिन थाले । यूएस डलरको अधिमूल्यांकन भएकाले यसलाई सच्याउनु पर्छ भन्ने अमेरिकाले ठान्यो । त्यसैले १९७१ मा राष्ट्रपति निक्सनले सुन सँगको परिवत्र्यतालाई अस्थायी रुपमा हटाए ।</p>



<p>अन्य केहि प्रमुख देशहरुले पनि बिस्तारै स्थिर प्रणालीलाई तोडे । र, १९७३ मा ब्रेटन उड्स सिस्टम् नै हट्यो ।&nbsp; ब्रेटन उड्स सिस्टमको आडमा ढुक्क भएर जोखिम उठाउदै कारोवार गरिरहेको हरस्ट्याट बैंक बन्द हुन पुग्यो । र, अन्य धेरैलाई यस्को असर पर्यो । यस घटनाले जी–१० राष्ट्रका केन्द्रिय बैंकका गभर्नरहरुलाई सुधारात्मक कदम चाल्नका लागि घच्घच्यायो ।</p>



<p><strong>बासेल कमिटी अन् बैकिङ सुपरभिजन</strong><br>हरस्याट घटना पछि जी–१० राष्ट्रका केन्द्रिय बैंकका गभर्नरहरु बासेलमा जम्मा भए । पुँजीका तुलनामा अत्यधिक जोखिम उठाएकाले हरस्ट्याट घटना घटेको निचोड निकाले ।<br><br>यस्ता घटनाबाट बैकिङ क्षेत्रलाई&nbsp; जोगाउन नियमन र सुपरिवेक्षण अझ प्रभावकारी तरिकाले गर्नुपर्ने निचोड समेत निकाले । र, त्यसका लागि सन् १९७४ मा एउटा समिति पनि गठन गरे ।</p>



<p>बासेल स्वीटजरल्याण्डको जनसंख्याको दृष्टिकोणले तेस्रो ठूलो शहरको नाम हो । यो फ्रान्स र जमर्नीको सीमा नजिकै अबस्थित छ ।</p>



<p>विश्वभर सुपरिवेक्षण क्षमता र गुणस्तर बढाइ बित्तीय स्थिरता कायम गर्ने उद्देश्यकासाथ उक्त समितिको गठन गरिएको थियो । बासेलमा बैठक बसेकाले पछि यस समितिलाई ‘बासेल कमिटी अन बैकिङ्&nbsp; सुपरभिजन’ भनेर नामाकरण गरियो ।</p>



<p><strong>बासेल – १</strong><br>बासेल समिति गठन भएपछि विश्वभर वित्तीय स्थिरता कायम गर्ने प्रयास भयो । तर, बैंकिङ क्षेत्रमा भने जोखिम झन् बढ्दै गयो ।</p>



<p>यसैबीच सन् १९८० को दशकतिर ल्याटिन अमेरिकामा कर्जा संकट आयो । पुँजी अपर्याप्त भएकाले यस्ता घटना बढेको निचोड बासेल समितिले निकाल्यो । त्यसैले, यस्ता जोखिम न्यूनीकरण गर्ने उद्देश्यले पुँजी गणना विधि उल्लेख गरिएको परामर्श पत्र सन् १९८७ मा उक्त समितिले प्रकाशन गर्यो ।</p>



<p>सन् १९८८ मा ‘जी – १०’ का गभर्नरहरुले उक्त परामर्शपत्रलाई स्वीकृत गरे । र, त्यसलाई ‘बासेल क्यापिटल एकर्ड १९८८’ नामाकरण गरी प्रकाशित गरे ।</p>



<p>यस परामर्शपत्रमा जोखिम भारित सम्पत्तिका आधारमा कम्तीमा ८ प्रतिशत जम्मापुँजी कोष हुनुपर्ने उल्लेख गरिएको थियो । यसैलाई ‘बासेल–१’ भन्ने गरिन्छ ।<br>&nbsp;<br>१९८८ एकर्डलाई पटक पटक शंसोधन गरियो । सन् १९९६ मा शंसोधन गर्दा बजार जोखिमलाई&nbsp; समेत समेटियो । बजार जोखिम गणना गर्दा भार (भ्यालु एट रिस्क) का आधारमा पुँजी कायम गर्नुपर्ने नयाँ व्यवस्थासमेत उल्लेख गरियो ।</p>



<p><strong>बियरिङ् बैंकको असफलता</strong><br>लण्डन स्थित ‘बियरिङ्’ बैंक सिंगापुरमा पनि संचालित थियो । तर, दुर्भाग्य १९९५ को फेब्रुअरीमा यो बन्द हुन पुग्यो । निक्लिसन भन्ने एउटा कर्मचारीको गल्तीले बैंक बन्द गर्नुपर्ने अबस्थामा पुगेको थियो ।<br>&nbsp;<br>जोखिम व्यवस्थापनका दृष्टिकोणबाट लेखांकन र हिसाब मिलान गर्ने जिम्मेवारी एकै कर्मचारीलाई दिइदैन । तर, निक्लिसनलाई दुबै जिम्मेवारी दिइएको थियो ।<br>&nbsp;<br>आफुलाई प्राप्त त्यो अधिकारको दुरुपयोग गर्दै निक्लिसनले फ्युचर मार्केटमा खेल्न थाल्यो । ती कारोवारबाट घाटा हुंदै गयो । तर, घाटा देखाएमा व्यवस्थापनले नराम्रो दृष्टिकोणले हेर्छ भन्ने उस्ले ठान्यो ।</p>



<p>त्यसैले, ‘८८८८८’ नम्बरको ‘इरर्’’ खाता खोलि घाटालाई नाफा देखाइ मुख्य कार्यालय लण्डनलाई रिर्पोट गर्न थाल्यो । लण्डन कार्यालयबाट राम्रो काम गरेको भन्दै प्रशंसा समेत पायो ।</p>



<p>तर, यो खेल धेरै दिन लुक्न सकेन । यसैबीच&nbsp; ‘कोबे भूकम्प’ गयो । जस्ले गर्दा एशियाको बित्तीय अवस्थामा संकट आयो । यतिबेलासम्म बियरिङ् बैंक सिंगापुरले १ अरब ४० करोड अमेरिकी डलर घाटा खाइसकेको थियो । यो घाटा पुँजीको तुलनामा दुई गुना वढी थियो । त्यहि घटनाले बैंकलाई बन्द समेत गरायो ।</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://subediamrit471.github.io/letslearn/2020/03/01/the-heart-of-nintendos-new-console-isnt-the-switch/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
